<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd to the societies for reformation of manners, in the cities of London and Westminster, Nov. 15, 1697 by John Shower.</title>
            <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 78 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3689</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17773</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13164130</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13164130</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98209</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60152)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98209)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 751:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd to the societies for reformation of manners, in the cities of London and Westminster, Nov. 15, 1697 by John Shower.</title>
                  <author>Shower, John, 1657-1715.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 66, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Lawrence ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 66.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[4] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah LIX, 4 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98209:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98209:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACH'D to the SOCIETIES FOR <hi>Reformation of</hi> MANNERS, IN THE Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter, Nov.</hi> 15. 1697. By <hi>JOHN SHOWER. Publiſhed at the Deſire of the ſaid</hi> SOCIETIES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> at the <hi>Angel,</hi> in the <hi>Poultry,</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Compter.</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:98209:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98209:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ISAIAH LiX. 4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>None calleth for Juſtice.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>'TIS certain, that the Principles and Duties of Natural Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are ſuppoſed, confirmed, and enforced by the Chriſtian. The Grace of God, which bringeth Salvation, teacheth and obligeth us, to live ſoberly and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly, as well as Godly. But how a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhing is the Kindneſs and Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? that God has ſhown ſuch regard to thoſe parts of Morality, which relate to the Good of Mankind, as to prefer them before his own Worſhip? That the Duties of the Law of Nature, are to take place of thoſe of poſitive Inſtitution; That he had rather we ſhould expreſs our Love to one another, and by Charity and Mercy do good in the World, than be honoured himſelf by Sacrifice, when that cannot be without Prejudice to our Neigbour. It muſt therefore be a very
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98209:3"/> miſtaken Notion of Religion, to imagine that any can be a very good Chriſtian, that is not a very good Man. For Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is not deſigned only for the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of particular Souls in another Life, but for the Welfare of Mankind, as uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Societies in this World. And for that purpoſe God hath appointed Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates as his Ordinance, and required our Obedience for Conſcience ſake. He hath commanded us to pray for Kings, and all in Authority under them, and to aſſiſt them to our utmoſt, that they may not bear the Sword in vain. We are to riſe up for them againſt the Evil-doers, and ſtand up for them againſt the Workers of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> cxvi. 9.</note> We are to forward and promote the Adminiſtration of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and even to <hi>call for it,</hi> where that is needful, and may ſerve a publick Good.</p>
            <p>THE Neglect of this, and the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Indifferency and Remiſneſs of private Perſons, as to the Execution of Juſtice, is here complained of, as one of thoſe things that made the <hi>Jews</hi> in danger of publick Judgments. For when National Calamity is here threatned, this is aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98209:3"/> as one of thoſe things that procured it, That <hi>there was none called for Juſtice, i. e.</hi> very Few amongſt them did concern themſelves, as private Perſons, to have Publick Juſtice duely adminiſtred. And 'tis further added, or <hi>pleadeth for Truth;</hi> or, as ſome render the Words, <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth truely.</hi> That is, Private Perſons, are careleſs and indifferent as to all ſuch Matters; and Publick Magiſtrates, are negligent and faulty as to what belongs to them.</p>
            <p>'TIS the former Expreſſion, <hi>None calls for Juſtice,</hi> that I am now to conſider, with reſpect to <hi>Private</hi> Perſons: For, thanks be to God, there are Faithful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates in and about the City, who are ready to do their Duty in the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Juſtice, if Private Perſons will but do theirs in calling for it.</p>
            <p>MY Deſign from this Paſſage, is, <hi>First,</hi> To manifeſt that this is the Duty of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Perſons, which will at once vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate your worthy Undertaking, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage you to proceed, and perſwade others to joyn with you. <hi>Secondly,</hi> To conſider ſome of the Objections, that may diſhearten others from doing ſo, and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98209:4"/> weaken your own Hands. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I ſhall take the Liberty to adviſe ſome things, that may help to attain your great End, the Reformation of Manners, and may render your Endeavours herein ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted with God, and all good Men. And, <hi>Laſtly,</hi> From ſeveral Conſiderations, I ſhall endeavour to ſtir you up to call for Juſtice.</p>
            <p n="1">I. FOR the Proof, That this is a <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> in Private Perſons, we need but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how it is here complained of in the <hi>Jews,</hi> as one of thoſe Iniquities which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated between God and them, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to hide his Face, that he would not hear their Prayers, <hi>Ver.</hi> 2. It is joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Lying and Cheating, with Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and Murther, and other Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that few or none had the Zeal and Courage, the Honeſty and Integrity, to excite and aſſiſt the Magiſtrate in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Juſtice, whereby the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God might be aſſerted, and the Authority of his Laws maintained, by the Puniſhment of Tranſgreſſors. To make you the more ſenſible that this is part of your Duty, I ſhall beſpeak you. <hi>Firſt,</hi> As <hi>Men,</hi> and Members of a publick Society,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98209:4"/> and ſo argue from the Principles of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Religion. <hi>Secondly,</hi> As <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who acknowledge the Holy Scriptures, and profeſs to own Revealed Religion. And, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſidered as in a private Capacity, with reference to your own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies and Relations; where I ſhall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt it to be, not only your Duty, but your Intereſt, to be concerned for the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Juſtice.</p>
            <p n="1">1. AS MEN. Our general Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to Mankind, as we are Men, are more antient, and more indiſpenſible, than any particular ones that can be ſuperadded; ſo that by the Law of Nature we are bound to do good to all Men, as we have Opportunity, and to promote the Good of the Place where we live, and of the Community whereof we are Members. From a Principle of Love to the Society and to our ſelves alſo: for I my ſelf and mine ſhall be involved in the Common Ruine. This is ſo Evident, that many an honeſt Heathen would have condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him as unworthy the Name of a Man, who ſhould prefer his Eſtate, his Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or Life, before the Common Good. Now when the Laws of God, and the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98209:5"/> Land, have provided for the Puniſhment of ſuch Offences as manifeſtly tend to the Ruine of the Society, whereof I am a Member, it muſt needs be my Duty, by the Law of Nature, to do what I can to prevent it. For if ſuch and ſuch Laws are for the Publick Good, and the Peace and Happineſs of a Nation is promoted by obſerving them; and the Tranſgreſſors of ſuch Laws be not puniſhed, the Laws themſelves are inſignificant, and the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Miſchiefs, they were deſigned to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, cannot be kept off, for want of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution.</p>
            <p>EVERY one reckons by the Light of Nature, it is his Duty to aſſiſt his Neighbour, as a <hi>Witneſs</hi> or otherwiſe, that Right may take place, and Juſtice be adminiſtred in <hi>Civil Matters;</hi> that in caſe his Perſon be aſſaulted, or his Goods ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, or what is his juſt Due be detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he may have the Satisfaction of the Law; There is the ſame, or greater Reaſon, in <hi>Criminal</hi> Matters, where the Puniſhment of the Offence is for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of GOD, and for the Publick Good; and where a Reparation can no otherwiſe be made, but by the Suffering
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98209:5"/> of the Offender, which in Matters of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty may be done by the Payment of ſo much Money.</p>
            <p>AND how can an honeſt Magiſtrate, for want of Legal Conviction, puniſh the Guilty, if he never ſo much deſire it? Let him be never ſo well qualified for his Office, and reſolv'd to be faithful, yet if none will complain of the Breach of the Laws, and give him an Account by whom they are broken, and bear Witneſs in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to Legal Conviction, what can he do as a Terror to evil Doers? It will ſignifie little to have never ſo many good Laws, or good Magiſtrates: For Offenders will be as no Offenders, if there be none to witneſs againſt them: And the wiſeſt and beſt Laws will be as none if they be not executed. And how can they be put in Execution by the Magiſtrate, if there be none to acquaint him by whom they are tranſgreſs'd, <hi>i. e.</hi> if none will <hi>call for Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice?</hi> In many caſes, where the Number, Intereſt, and Character of the Offenders is conſiderable, a Magiſtrate may not have the Courage to do it, if he had the Opportunity, without the Countenance and Encouragement of other Men. And
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98209:6"/> yet moſt uſually, the Puniſhment of one Great Criminal might do more good, than of twenty meaner ones, as his Example and Influence did more hurt. This muſt needs hearten and encourage a good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to do his Duty, when, beſides the Authority of his Office, and the Power of the Law, and his own particular Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, he is back'd and aſſiſted by his Fellow Citizens: For hereby his Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation will be the better ſecured, if he be faithful: In all Converſations and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Meetings, there will be ſome of his Neighbours and Acquaintance, ready to abet his Cauſe, if he ſhould be reflected on. And this will facilitate the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Juſtice by ſucceeding Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates: And if any of you be hereafter call'd to ſerve your Country in a publick Station, what you do now in a private Capacity will enable you to do more Good hereafter in a publick one.</p>
            <p>AS to Treaſons, and Murders, and Thefts, Men do not reckon themſelves at liberty to be <hi>Neuters,</hi> but theſe leſſer Crimes make way for greater. And it is the Intereſt of any Government, and even of the Supream Magiſtrate himſelf,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98209:6"/> that ill Manners be corrected, and leſſer Criminals puniſhed; becauſe it is by the Commiſſion of leſſer Crimes, that Men are prepared and hardened to venture up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on greater. If the Laws, that threaten only Correction, Impriſonment, or a Fine, be neglected and deſpiſed; ſuch as threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Death, will in time have little Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: For he that will Swear and Curſe, and be Drunk, and commit Adultery, and matters not the Hazard of his Health and Life, by a Courſe of Debauchery, will in a little time be hardened, ſo as to deſpiſe Death by the Sword of Juſtice. 'Tis there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Intereſt of any Government, to have ill Manners corrected, as a proper Means to prevent greater Crimes, where the Puniſhment is Capital.</p>
            <p>IT ought likewiſe to be conſidered, that there is the ſame Contempt of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, if not greater, in tranſgreſſing thoſe Laws, to which leſſer Puniſhments are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, as where the Offender muſt <hi>die</hi> for it; the Difference of the Puniſhment, is not becauſe there is leſs Contempt of the Law, and of the Law-giver, in the one caſe, than in the other; but becauſe the evil Conſequences are not the ſame:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98209:7"/> For the Voluntary allowed Neglect or Breach of any part of the Law, renders us guilty of the Violation of the whole, which was enacted by the ſame Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. You muſt therefore remember, that tho' ſuch Inſtances of Immorality, as you endeavour to puniſh, have not ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Tendency, as Murder and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to bring publick Confuſion and Ruine; yet not only doth the one pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for the other, but there is as mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt a Contempt of Divine and Humane Authority in theſe, as in the moſt Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Offences.</p>
            <p>BUT whether the Crimes be greater or ſmaller, the Ends of Puniſhment are ſuch as cannot be attain'd, without the Aſſiſtance of private Perſons, that the Laws made for the common Good be put in Execution.</p>
            <p>THE Three great Ends of Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are either, <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Amendment of the particular guilty Perſon. <hi>Secondly,</hi> The making Others better, or preventing the like Sin in others by the Warning gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Or, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The Publick Security, promoted, by upholding the Honour of the Law, and vindicating the Authority of the Law-giver.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98209:7"/>
            <p n="1">1. ONE End of Puniſhment, annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to good and righteous Laws, is the Amendment of the guilty Perſon. Tho' Puniſhment alone will not teach him how to amend his Life; it may convince him that it needs to be reformed. He knows by what he ſuffers, that he hath not done as he ſhould, and ſo may next conſider how to do better, and reſolve upon it. Many Men, by their <hi>Calamities</hi> in the World, by Sickneſs, and Poverty, and Shame, and the like, have been brought to conſider their evil Ways, and, we hope, to amend them. Much more may we hope it, when the Suffering is the immediate direct Puniſhment, inflicted by the Laws of the Country for ſuch a Crime. In that caſe, the Offender cannot turn his Eyes from the Occaſion and Cauſe of his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, or impute it to any thing elſe, as Men commonly do in other caſes. For Inſtance, If a common Swearer be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed in his Purſe, or a lewd Perſon ſent to the Houſe of Correction; they cannot impute their Sufferings to any other Cauſe, than to the Faults for which they have been puniſhed. And who knows, but that God, who delights not in the Death
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98209:8"/> of Sinners, may give them Repentance, and their preſent Sufferings help to ſave them from Eternal ones? There have doubtleſs been many, who have ſinned themſelves within a Step of Hell, who have run into the vileſt Debaucheries, and ſo to the very Brink of Ruine, that the very Flames of the bottomleſs Pit have even ſinged their Garments, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken hold of the Hair of their Heads; who have yet been plucked as Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands out of the Burning, and have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feignedly repented, and turned to God even in <hi>Newgate.</hi> Concerning divers ſuch, we may hope, that tho' they fell under the Sword of the Civil Magiſtrate; yet, by Repentance towards God, and Faith in our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, they eſcaped E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Condemnation. And there might be more Inſtances of this kind, were there more care taken to aſſiſt condemned Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners before their Execution; our Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in preparing them for another World, might be more ſucceſsful, than uſually it is upon Perſons on a ſick Bed.</p>
            <p>BUT while I mention Charity to the Souls of Condemned Malefactors, I am perſwaded there would be fewer ſuch, if
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98209:8"/> better Proviſion were made of <hi>Work</hi> and <hi>Work-houſes</hi> for the Poor: Becauſe Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Poverty are the great Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to many of thoſe Vices that fill the Priſons and Houſes of Correction. There is more hope however, where the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſhort of Death, and the guilty Perſon it may be comes from a good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and had Religious Parents, and hath but lately caſt off the Fetters of his Education, when 'tis not long that he hath been taken in the ſnare of the Devil, there is the more hope that ſuch a one may be brought to conſider himſelf, by ſuch leſſer Puniſhment, and ſo reform.</p>
            <p n="2">2. ANOTHER End of Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is to warn others not to tranſgreſs in the like kind. And ſo it is rather an Act of Mercy, than Revenge; the End of it not being ſo much to retaliate the Evil on the Offender, as to do good to Others, and to keep them from the like Offences. <hi>Smite a Scorner,</hi> ſays the Wiſe Man, one that is an obſtinate and inſolent Offender,<note place="margin">19 Prov. 25.</note> 
               <hi>and the Simple will beware.</hi> Such as were like to ſin by Inadvertency or ill Example,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98209:9"/> will take warning.<note place="margin">25 Chap. 11.</note> 
               <hi>When the Scorners are Puniſhed, the Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are made Wiſe.</hi> If one Sinner deſtroy much good, if one root of Bitterneſs may defile many; the Impunity of Criminals upon this account muſt needs be a great Miſchief, as likely to ſpread the Infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on through the whole Neighbourhood, Street, and City: And ſo 'tis every Mans concern, to have his Neighbours Child or Servant Puniſhed for ſuch Faults, from which he would preſerve his own: And I need not tell you how much greater Influence bad Examples have, than good ones; you know that <hi>Health</hi> is not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated, as Diſeaſes are.</p>
            <p n="3">3. PUNISHMENT is an Act of Government, and hath relation to the Law; and ſo one End of it is to preſerve the Authority of the Laws, and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Magiſtrate, who is concerned for the Publick Good.<note place="margin">See the Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter</hi>'s Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings of Chriſt. <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. <hi>Grotius</hi> de Satisf. Cap. 2.</note> The reaſon, here, of Puniſhment, is not ſo much becauſe a Law is broken, as becauſe, if it be not puniſhed, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Law, and Lawgiver, can
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98209:9"/> never be upheld; and that is neceſſary, or the Community can never be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd. And where the Offence to be puniſhed, is againſt GOD and the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Laws; the Puniſhment is due to the Honour of GOD, and to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Good; and 'tis not in a Private Mans Power to forgive the Injury to the Publick, as he may do a pecuniary Debt that is owing to himſelf. <hi>Vengeance,</hi> ſays God, <hi>is mine;</hi> i. e. the inflicting of Puniſhment belongs to me. In him all manner of Right is primarily and origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally lodged, as the great Lord and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietor of all. And every Injury and Injuſtice to another, either private, or publick, redounds upon Him as the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of the World. The deciſion of Right and Wrong, the diſtribution of Rewards and Puniſhments, appertains to him. <hi>Vengeance,</hi>as taken for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting of Puniſhment, is his undoubted Prerogative, his unalienable Right: It belongs to him, and to thoſe only whom he appoints to be <hi>his Miniſters to execute WRATH on ſuch as do evil.</hi> And we are not only, to ſuppoſe the reaſon of this to be the Danger that may accrue to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98209:10"/> Society by the Impunity of Crimes, but becauſe of the Diſhonour and Affront that is offer'd to GOD, as the Governour of the World. He aſſumes Anger, Wrath, and Jealouſie, to ſhow he minds his own Glory, and will not bear Contempt, but avenge it. And to make Tranſgreſſors ſuffer, is for the Reparation of God's in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd Honour, as well as for the Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Society. It cannot therefore un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>become a good Man to call for <hi>Juſtice, it being his Duty on all theſe accounts</hi> to further and promote it.</p>
            <p>THESE things will concern us as we are Men, under the Obligation of the Law of Nature.</p>
            <p n="2">2. LET me beſpeak you, as you are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and profeſs to own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Religion, and the Authority of the Holy Scriptures. 'Tis not the duty of Magiſtrates and Miniſters only, but of all the Followers of Chriſt, to be the Salt of the Earth, and the Lights of the World, in their ſeveral places. Every Member is bound to promote the welfare of the whole Body, according to his Capacity. Every Chriſtian muſt imitate his Maſter, who went about
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98209:10"/> doing good. He is created, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed, and ſanctified, for it, as the Tree is made for the Fruit. Many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout Perſons may think, if they were Rich enough to live without bodily Labour, and could ſpend all their time in Meditation, and Prayer, and hearing Sermons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That this were the happieſt Life in the World. The <hi>Popiſh Nuns</hi> and <hi>Fryars</hi> are under this miſtake. But no Man is made for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alone, we are Members of Society: We muſt do good to Others, and in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, we take Care of our own Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Our Lord has taught us to pray, that the Name of God may be Sanctified, and ſhall we ſilently ſuffer it to be profaned? And his Kingdom come, and ſhall we do nothing that it may take place? And his Will be done on Earth, as in Heaven; without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring this, we contradict our own Prayers. And when we deſire the Will of God may be done, we mean it by <hi>Others,</hi> as well as our ſelves. And is it not the Will of God, that ſuch Offences ſhould be Puniſhed? We beg Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our own Sins, and the Sins of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98209:11"/> the Nation; Can we do it uprightly, and not endeavour Reformation? We may not ſuffer Sin upon Others, any more than allow it in our ſelves. The Scripture Examples, of <hi>Zerubbabel, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah, Ezra, &amp;c.</hi> may be urged to this purpoſe, as you have heard in ſome former Sermons, and I hope with very good Effect.</p>
            <p>BUT let me here reaſon with you a little. Is it fit for <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned, that Juſtice be done between Man and Man, as to their Lives, Eſtates, and Civil Rights; and ſhall we be more indifferent as to thoſe Laws, where the Honour of GOD, and of our Bleſſed Redeemer, are more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately concerned? If a notorious Cheat or Thief be diſcovered and taken, what general Rejoycing is there in the City! What Crowds will attend him to the Juſtice of Peace, to the Priſon, to the Seſſions-Houſe, to the Pillory! Is it only, becauſe your ſelves may one time or other be injured by ſuch a Crime, or have been ſo? Doubtleſs, <hi>in Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Caſes,</hi> there is more reaſon to aſſiſt, and more reaſon to rejoyce, as theſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98209:11"/> Offenders are the Peſts of Humane Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety; and as their Crimes do carry an open Affront to Heaven. Is the cheating of you of a little Money ſo great a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the defrauding you in a Bill of Exchange, or a Bank Note, ſo very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, that every one is ready to aſſiſt to have ſuch a Fellow puniſhed? And is there not more reaſon in the other Caſe? Is the value of Ten or Twenty Pounds more to be regarded, than the Vertue, Honour, Safety, Health, Life, and Soul, of your Relations and Neighbours, which may be corrupted and deſtroyed by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed Vice, and Examples of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery?</p>
            <p>YOU know, you are not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice and tempt Others to Sin; but are you not likewiſe to prevent others from being tempted? You may not lay a ſtumbling block in anothers way, to make him fall; but if you ſee him rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to caſt himſelf down a Precipice, will you do nothing to prevent it? <hi>Nehemiah</hi> charges the Rulers for break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Sabbath, becauſe they did not reſtrain others from bearing Burthens. How dear did it coſt <hi>Ely,</hi> and his Houſe,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98209:12"/> that, when his Sons made themſelves vile, he reſtrained them not! Tho' <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> ſpake to the <hi>Jews</hi> on the behalf of Chriſt as Innocent; yet is he charged with his Murther, for not doing all that he could to hinder it. We may many ways <hi>partake of other Mens Sins,</hi> and this doubtleſs is one, If we do not what we may and ought to prevent them. In which Caſe we likewiſe ſhare in all the ill Conſequences of their Iniquity, in all the Miſchiefs that follow upon the City and Nation, by ſuch Impuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Let me expreſs this in the better words of<note n="*" place="margin">Serm. 1. ad Magiſtratum. 29 Job. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Biſhop Sanderſon,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">You countenance, ſays he, the Diſorders, that by Juſtice may be ſuppreſſed; You diſarm Innocency, that Juſtice would protect; You baniſh Peace, which by Juſtice is maintained; You are Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to the King and his Throne, which by Juſtice is eſtabliſhed; and you pull down on the City and the Nation the publick Plagues and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, which the Execution of Juſtice would avert.</q> Is it not then your duty, as Chriſtians, to promote
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98209:12"/> and forward the Execution of Juſtice, when thereby you contribute to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Diſorders, to protect Innocency, to maintain Peace, to ſecure the King and State, and to turn away publick Judgments from the Land?</p>
            <p>SIRS, We are all Chriſtians, the Duty is common to us all, the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is equal. 'Tis what we are all concerned in, and agree in; becauſe by our <hi>Baptiſm</hi> we are all engaged to fight under the Banner of Chriſt, in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Warfare againſt the Devil and his Angels. And 'tis obſervable, that when our Saviour was charged as a Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate with Satan in working Miracles, he tells us, (and it is repeated by three Evangeliſts) that he was ſo far from that, that he looked upon that Man for his Enemy, who would not ſerve him in oppoſition to the Devils Kingdom and Intereſt. <hi>He that is not with me, is against me; and he that gathereth not with me, ſcattereth abroad,</hi> Matth. 12.30. Chriſt hath his Kingdom to carry on in the World, and Satan hath his: You muſt either be for advancing the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt againſt the Devil, or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98209:13"/> you joyn in Confederacy with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil againſt the Son of God and his Kingdom. I remember what <hi>Jehu</hi> ſaid in another caſe, but not very different, (when he was to Execute Judgment, by Gods command, on the whole Houſe of <hi>Ahab,) Who is on my ſide?</hi> cryed <hi>Jehu,</hi> Who is on my ſide? I may put the like Queſtion this day, or rather beg that you would to your ſelves, <hi>Which ſide will you take?</hi> For you cannot be <hi>Newters.</hi> Which ſide will you take; For Reformation? Or for Profaneneſs? For ſuppreſſing Vice, or for letting it alone? That is, Will you be <hi>for Chriſt,</hi> or <hi>for the Devil?</hi> You muſt be Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous to your Lord, and unfaithful to your Baptiſmal Vow, if you do not joyn heartily againſt the Intereſt of the Devil, in ſo plain and publick a Caſe as this.</p>
            <p>AND among all ſorts of Chriſtians, that have written againſt Perſecution, and about the Power of the Magiſtrate as to Matters of Religion, we find that the greateſt Sticklers for the moſt <hi>unlimited Toleration,</hi> as to different Sentiments about Matters of Faith, and Worſhip; do yet
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98209:13"/> all agree, that theſe Inſtances of Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality do properly come under the Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of the Civil Magiſtrate, as having a mighty Influence upon Publick Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, being very prejudicial to the Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of it. So that no Man can complain of Perſecution for his Opinions, when he is puniſhed for ſuch groſs Immoralities a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Laws of God and the Land. No <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> no <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> who differ in leſſer Matters as to Faith and Worſhip, will plead for the Allowance of ſuch Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of Manners, and Debauchery of Life, as you endeavour to ſuppreſs.</p>
            <p>IF it ſhould be ſaid, that I am miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken here: For all Chriſtians do not agree about <hi>the Morality of the Sabbath,</hi> and therefore it is hard to puniſh Men for the Profanation of it. <hi>I anſwer,</hi> that grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome good Men may have given Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections about the Obſervation of the Lord's Day, that cannot be warranted from the Word of God, as reducing it too much to a weariſome bodily Exerciſe, yet have we enough to confirm our Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Practice as to <hi>the Lord's Day,</hi> by conſidering the firſt Original and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Sabbath, and the Matter
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98209:14"/> of the <hi>Fourth Commandment;</hi> (And when all the other Nine are granted to be of univerſal and perpetual Obligation, 'tis hard to conceive, that <hi>one</hi> of the <hi>ten</hi> ſhould concern <hi>only the Jews;</hi>) And conſidering the Practice of the Chriſtian Church in all Ages, and the Experience of a ſpecial Preſence and Bleſſing of God on the Publick Chriſtian Worſhip on ſuch a Weekly Day of Reſt; and that ſerious Religion was never obſerved to thrive and flouriſh, or be long preſerved, in any City, Family, or particular Soul, where this was neglected; Theſe, and the like things, are ſufficient for our Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification. But you my Brethren, that are Members of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> are peculiarly obliged to ſuppreſs the Profa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Weekly Sabbath; becauſe every Lord's Day, and oft'ner, you beg of God, <hi>to incline your Hearts to keep the Fourth Commandment,</hi> and that the <hi>Fourth,</hi> as well as the other <hi>Nine,</hi> may be <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten upon your Hearts,</hi> and obeyed in your Lives. Beſides what might be quoted out of the <hi>Homilies.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:98209:14"/>
            <p n="3">3. HAVING mentioned this of the Sabbath, I proceed, to conſider you in your Families, and Shops, and private Relations, and ſo to manifeſt it to be your <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> on that account, to have the Laws put in Execution, and particularly againſt the Profanation of the Lord's Day. For while your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Servants are employed in Civil Buſineſs, and Secular Affairs, on the Week-days, they are freed from many Temptations: But if they be not em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in Religious Exerciſes on the Lord's Day, if they are left to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to do nothing, or to do what they pleaſe; to ſtay at home, or go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; to attend the publick Worſhip, or not attend it, you expoſe them to ſuch Temptations, as many ways may be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to your ſelves, and in the end Deſtructive to them. There are Few, that come to a miſerable ſhameful Death in this World, but acknowledge this, and date their Wickedneſs and their Ruine from their neglecting to keep holy the Lord's Day.</p>
            <p>DO but Conſider how much the Peace and Safety of your Families, the Trade,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98209:15"/> the Riches and Proſperity of the City, (which conſiſts of particular Families,) is owing to good Laws, and to the Terror of the annexed Puniſhments; and you will hereby diſcern your own <hi>Intereſt</hi> ſo wrapp'd up in the Publick, as to infer your <hi>Duty</hi> to promote the Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Juſtice. Murders would be more frequently committed, were it not for the Terror of the Law. Robberies and Burglaries would be more common, were it not for the Severity of the Puniſhment. And that leſſer Thefts and Frauds, in buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſelling, are more common, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Penalty is ſmall if diſcovered, and the Means of Proſecution chargeable, There is very much reaſon to think, that 'tis not <hi>Conſcience,</hi> ſo much as the Dread of Temporal Puniſhment, that makes you ſafe in your Houſes, and quiet in the Poſſeſſion of what you enjoy.</p>
            <p>AS to the Suppreſſion of Profaneneſs and Debauchery, let Parents and Maſters conſider it, that 'tis more than poſſible, that ſome of thoſe Offenders, (who might be reclaimed by ſeaſonable Correction, but for want of it go on, and are harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Sin;) may be related hereafter to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98209:15"/> ſome of your Families, by the Marriage of a Son or Daughter, or other Relation: And ſo you and yours may ſmart by the ill Effects of that Wickedneſs, which Faithfulneſs and Zeal in your preſent Undertaking might reſtrain and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</p>
            <p>NEED I mind you of the Routs and Riots, the Quarrels, and Contentions, and Murthers, occaſioned by <hi>Drunkeneſs;</hi> of the Poverty and Ruine of a Multitude of Families, by that, and other expenſive Vices: Whereby Men not only undo themſelves, but rob thoſe for whom they ought to make Proviſion. Can you be ignorant of the horrid Confuſion in Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and the ſad Train of other ill Conſequences, as to Health, and Life, and Honour, and Eſtate, which is the Fruit of Lewdneſs and Uncleanneſs? Are you not ſenſible of the Advantage to your Families, by Purity, and Chaſtity, and keeping the Marriage Bed undefiled? and that by Drunkenneſs and Uncleanneſs Men are prepared for any other Villany they may be tempted to commit?</p>
            <p>CAN you be ſafe, as to your Perſons or Eſtates, good Name, or Life, while,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98209:16"/> by common and cuſtomary Swearing, the Reverence and Awe of an <hi>Oath</hi> is loſt, and the Obligation of it forgotten? What Truſt or Dependance can there rationally be given to the Teſtimony of ſuch a one, as a <hi>Witneſs</hi> or <hi>Juryman,</hi> who daily takes the Name of God in vain in his ordinary Diſcourſe? To this is owing very much the dreadful Guilt of Perjury and Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, that is more complained of in this Age, than it may be in any other.</p>
            <p>AS to the Buſineſs of <hi>Trade,</hi> let me reaſon with you, Would you not ſooner truſt a ſober honeſt Man, that hath but half the Eſtate of a lewd Debauchee? As knowing, in a little while the latter may be brought to a Morſel of Bread; and that many have been ſo, who once fared deliciouſly every Day; but by their Vices have ſquandred away great Eſtates, and been reduced to that Poverty, as to want a Dinner? Not only diſabled from pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Debts, if they had a Mind to it, but knew not how to get Bread. (I ſay, paying their Debts, <hi>if they had a Mind to it,</hi> becauſe uſually they that will not pay their juſt Debts when able, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards would do it, and have it not.)
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98209:16"/> But there is nothing is the undoing of Tradeſmen, like the Luſts and Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their Partners, and Correſpondents, their Cuſtomers, and their Debtors. How many a worthy Citizen has been bankrupt by other Mens Crimes, and not by his own? which, if they had been ſuppreſſed and puniſhed formerly, the Cries, and Tears, and Ruine of many a poor Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phan, and helpleſs Widow in this City, might have been prevented.</p>
            <p>I hope you can feel the Weight and Force of theſe Things, your own Thoughts may enlarge them. And even ſuch Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments may have ſome good Effect, where the Men perſwaded by them to do good, may not act out of a good Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, but only as wiſe in their Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For a covetous Father would be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Gaming and Prodigality of his Son, without any regard to God, or the publick Good. (As many that had Abby Lands, were againſt Popery:) But God often uſes Vice againſt Vice, otherwiſe Kingdoms and Churches muſt ſuffer more, or be ſaved by Miracle.</p>
            <p>BUT after all that I have ſaid, there is no Duty ſo plain, (tho' Intereſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nected
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98209:17"/> with it,) againſt which ſomething will not be ſaid, to diſcourage and hinder the Practice, I therefore come to anſwer an Objection or two, by which your Hands may be weakened, or others hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered from joining with you in this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Deſign. And,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It may be ſaid, <q rend="inline">That 'tis not ſo very Honourable and Genteel, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form againſt other Men for their ill Manners; 'tis more than we need, to be thus buſie in other Mens Matters; There is a certain Obloquy and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach inſeparable from ſuch Work, and by the Generality of the World fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened upon all that will meddle in it, who will not live quietly by their Neighbours, tho' they be not ſo good as they ſhould be.</q>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. AS to the Matter of <hi>Reproach.</hi> This is the more neceſſary to be taken notice of, not only as the moſt obvious; but becauſe many, who knew not the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods that you obſerve, and the Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Care you take in your Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and the very good Effect it hath already had, and how exactly you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to keep to the Laws of God
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98209:17"/> and the Land; many, I ſay, that knew not this, had not ſo good Thoughts of your Undertaking at firſt, as now, and as many others we hope will, upon fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Acquaintance with your Deſign, and not think it a <hi>Reproach</hi> to join with you therein. As to the Perſons themſelves that are obnoxious to the Law, it would be very great Weakneſs, to neglect your Duty, and Wound your Conſcience, for fear of being ill ſpoken of by Such, whoſe good Word could gain you no Credit and Reputation.</p>
            <p>YOU have been told, how ſome of the Princes themſelves, of the firſt Rank and Dignity amongſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> did not think it beneath them, to inform againſt thoſe who tranſgreſſed the Law of God, tho' ſome of their own Rank and Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were of that Number. <hi>Ezra</hi> ix. There have been many wiſe Law-givers, who have propounded and promiſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, to Encourage Men to give true and faithful Information againſt Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals: Eſpecially for ſuch Crimes as greatly tend to the Prejudice of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. As the one hand they had ſevere Puniſhments for falſe Accuſers out of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98209:18"/> Revenge, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo on the other hand Publick Rewards have been promiſed, and publick Honours have been beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in ſuch Caſes of Information, by the <hi>Romans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I hope I need not uſe ſuch Topicks to You, to venture your Reputation in this Caſe; when you own your ſelves <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and I have minded you of your <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> You will not think it a Reproach to be true to <hi>that.</hi> You know the Example and Precepts of Chriſt, of doing good to the Evil, and bleſſing thoſe that curſe you, and praying for thoſe that deſpitefully uſe you. I therefore hope, you will not be diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, if you have not more Acceptance and Succeſs in the Diſcharge of your Duty, than God has promiſed. If you can honour Him, and promote a publick Good; the more you are reviled and ſcorned upon that account, the more praiſe-worthy: There will be the more Vertue and Grace to deſpiſe your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in that caſe. <q rend="inline">Let it periſh, ſhould you ſay, if I may but do good; But it is in God's Hand, as much as my Life. And will not He bear me out, if
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98209:18"/> I honeſtly and ſincerely deſire to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote his Glory? Am I a Chriſtian, and can I doubt it? And have I not found, as well as others, that I never conſult my own Reputation ſo much, as when I moſt heartily endeavour to be faithful to God and Conſcience?</q> For <hi>they that honour God, ſhall be honoured;</hi> and they that play the Hypocrite, ſhall be found out, and <hi>Lightly eſteemed.</hi> Thanks be to God, you have many Excellent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of all Perſuaſions to unite with. But if you had not, you ſhould not ſcruple to be God's Witneſſes in the World againſt <hi>Profaneſs;</hi> and to do all the Good you can, whether Others will, or will not, join with you. If this be to be vile, you muſt reſolve to be more vile. But you need not fear your Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: For God hath ſaid it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.17. <hi>Every Tongue that ſhall riſe in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt thee, thou ſhalt condemn, and this is the Heritage of the Servants of the Lord.</hi> When may you apply it, and hope for its Accompliſhment, if not in your Caſe?</p>
            <p>DO but Argue with your ſelves a little. Can it be a Diſhonour, to appear
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98209:19"/> for the Bleſſed God, and your Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, when the very Perſons you would reſtrain and puniſh, (very few excepted,) inwardly condemn Themſelves, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit You? for they know you are in the Right, and themſelves in the Wrong. Moſt of them know the Bible, and the Chriſtian Religion, and the Laws of God, and that you do but act according to your Duty. And, ſooner or later, they will all Juſtifie your Proceedings. Your Reputation will be cleared, if you hold on; as the eclipſed Moon, by keeping and continuing her Motion, recovers her Splendor. Your Righteouſneſs will break forth as the Light, to the Shame of all that have thought, or ſpoken hardly of your Undertaking.</p>
            <p>IT cannot be diſhonourable for <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> of the beſt Character or Quality, to engage in this Deſign, if they conſider the Nature and Uſe of the <hi>Grand Juries</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> which are choſen out of the beſt Families, Men of the beſt Sence, of the beſt Eſtates, and of the beſt Figure in their Country; and they come under an Oath, to make Enquiry of all Offences committed within their County, that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98209:19"/> ſhall come to their Knowledge: <hi>They are bound to inform the Court againſt Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals.</hi> Now if it be reckoned a very Honourable thing to ſerve as a Grand Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryman, at the Call of a Magiſtrate; it can never be faulty and ſcandalous, to do this voluntarily at the Call of GOD, for the Service of the publick Intereſt, and with the Countenance of Authority, as is your Caſe. And neither Grand Juries, nor Petty Juries, will ſignifie much, if GOD do not give you Succeſs in your <hi>Worthy Deſign and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would fain have it ſeriouſly Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, whether there be any thing that you unite for, that is <hi>in it ſelf Diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable:</hi> And if there be not, your inward Peace, by the Teſtimony of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that you endeavour to honour and obey GOD, will over-balance the Cenſures of Men. If you can help to reform, and ſo ſave a ſinful and polluted City and Nation from Ruine, (and your Example has already begun to influence other Nations, as well as other Parts of this;) you ſhall not then have need to be aſhamed of it. <hi>Let them be aſhamed, that tranſgreſs without Cauſe.</hi> Let them be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98209:20"/> aſhamed, that do ſuch things, that can have no other Fruit and Conſequence, without Repentance, but <hi>Everlaſting Shame.</hi> What little things, to a Man of Conſcience, ſhould be a few hard Words, reproachful Epithets, ill Names, dirty Language, to your Face, or behind your Back? If you cannot bear this for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well, may not Chriſt be aſhamed of you before his Father and his holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels? <hi>The Proud have had me greatly in Deriſion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.51.</note> ſays the Pſalmiſt, <hi>yet I have not decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from thy Law.</hi> If Men revile you, and ſpeak all manner of Evil againſt you, for Chriſt's ſake, for Obedience to him, for advancing his Intereſt, and ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Honour; <hi>Happy are ye, the Spirit of God, and of Glory, will reſt upon you.</hi> Was not <hi>Elias</hi> taken for the Troubler of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and the Apoſtles reviled as thoſe that turned the World upſide down; and the moſt unſufferable of Men; and <hi>S. Paul</hi> himſelf for a peſtilent, ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Fellow? Did not many of the Holy Martyrs die in the Flames, for endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to ſave Men from the Fire of Hell? But I hope I need not ſay more
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98209:20"/> to this Objection; your very Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſtianity is enough to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. ANOTHER Objection may be ſtarted, <q rend="inline">That you would not be ſerved ſo your ſelves: It is unjuſt for one Neighbour to accuſe another, one Gentleman, one Tradeſman or Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to accuſe another, and bear Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt him: If you were the faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Perſon, you would not be willing to be ſo dealt with; <hi>You muſt do to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as you would be done by, for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>How plauſible ſoever this may appear, I ſhall ſhew, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That it does not reach the Caſe that I am ſpeaking of. <hi>Secondly,</hi> I ſhall turn it upon you, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force that which I deſign in this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. THIS Paſſage of our Saviour doth not reach the Caſe. For it is not a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat and primary Rule of all Humane Actions towards other Men; nor an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute unlimited one: But is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as a Relief in other Caſes, where we are at a loſs, for want of a particular Rule. As if a Man fail in the World, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98209:21"/> afterwards get an Eſtate, whether he ſhould not pay the whole, doing as he would be done by. But it muſt be uſed only in things firſt Lawful by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rule; otherwiſe I may be obliged by the Authority of GOD in ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Law, to do that to Others, which it may be I would not be very willing to receive: But the Matter is not left to my Liberty, as being determined already. And there are many Caſes, where our own Will and Deſire of others treating us, would be a wrong Guide, a very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect and defective Rule. Eſpecially if the Matter be determined before, by any particular Divine and Humane Laws. If a Man be indebted to you, you would not think much if you Arreſt him, if he will not pay: Whereas, it may be, you would not be very willing he ſhould ſerve you ſo. So for a Magiſtrate, if he offends, it may be he would not care to be puniſhed. But think a little what is <hi>Juſt,</hi> and <hi>Reaſonable,</hi> and fit in this Caſe: And in ſuch Points only this Rule holds. He that is to inflict the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is doubtleſs under leſs Prejudice, and ſuppoſed to be a more Impartial
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98209:21"/> Judge, than the Offender that is to be puniſhed. And if you were in his Caſe, you would think and act, as he does; and therefore cannot reaſonably expect to eſcape now: For it would be Cruelty to the greater, and far better part of the Society, if ſuch Offences ſhould go un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall turn it upon you, to enforce that which I deſign in this Diſcourſe, from this very Rule, of <hi>doing to Others as you would be done by.</hi> Is there any of you, that is willing to be defrauded, in his Perſon, Eſtate, Name, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever unwilling to be puniſhed, when guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Were any of you a Magiſtrate? (and many of you may live to be ſo) Would you not deſire the Concurrence, the Countenance and Aſſiſtance of your Neighbours and Fellow-Citizens, in the Execution of your Office? Whatever you would reaſonably deſire and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove from Others in that caſe, you are now to render to them. And as to your Selves too, you will do well to keep this Rule in your Eye, in the purſuit of your great Deſign. And therefore to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate the offending Perſons, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98209:22"/> to deſire and ſeek their Repentance and Amendment: Not to magnifie or multiply their Faults, without Reaſon; but to put the faireſt Conſtruction upon their Words and Actions: If their Fault will admit of any Plea, Diminution or Excuſe, not to reject it, but to make the ſame Allowance to others, as, in the ſame Circumſtances, you would rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably deſire from any Honeſt Man.</p>
            <p>IN a Word, not to tranſgreſs the Bounds of Charity and Mercy, even in the Adminiſtration of Juſtice, becauſe you your ſelves would deſire it in the like Caſe. And on this Account, unleſs the Criminals be obſtinate and impudent, you will do well to treat them with Meekneſs, and Gentleneſs of Speech and Behaviour: For bitter and upbraiding Words, and a moroſe ſour Carriage, will but help to make them Obſtinate. And the Faults and Follies of Mankind, as well as their Sufferings in the World, are Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Pitty. Hard Words, rude and unkind Speeches, will do harm to young Sinners; and Mankind is ſo made, that they will hardly do good to any Body. However, remember to do as you would
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98209:22"/> be done by. And ſo I am led to give you ſome Advice before I was aware, with reference to your Proceedings, which is the <hi>Third Thing</hi> I propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>AND that which I have now ſaid, directs me to begin with this Counſel, <hi>Firſt,</hi> That tho' you ought to be Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, yet you muſt <hi>have Compaſſion, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a difference</hi> between ſome ſorts of Criminals and others. It is the Apoſtle's Advice, <hi>Jude</hi> 22. Tho' that may relate to the Governours of the Church, yet 'tis very applicable here. As there is a Difference in Crimes, and the Law makes a Difference in Puniſhment; ſo there is in Criminals. If it be the firſt or ſecond Fault, it is not all one Caſe, as with a hardened habituated Sinner. You will eaſily Apprehend, that a green Wound, and an old Ulcer, are not to be cured by the ſame Application. A ſharp Reproof, a ſerious Admonition, or a ſevere Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, may do more good on Some, than the ſevereſt Puniſhment on Others, who are paſt Shame. There are ſome who fall by Surprize, and not by Deliberation and cuſtomary Wickedneſs; and ſuch
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98209:23"/> ought to be pitied, and reſtored in the Spirit of Meekneſs: There is not ſo much of vicious Habit, and Stubbornneſs of Will, in ſuch Caſes, as of the Frailty of Humane Nature.</p>
            <p n="2">2. HOWEVER, you muſt be ſo far Impartial, notwithſtanding this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, as not to ſpare any Man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is of your Party and Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Matters of Religion: Nor to ſeek for Crimes and Offences in thoſe of <hi>one Party,</hi> rather than <hi>another.</hi> For ſuch Tranſgreſſions of the Law are equally faulty in all. Let Men pretend to what Strictneſs they will in Matters of poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Inſtitution and Worſhip, theſe Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moralities are heinous, and to be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Judges. Your Partiality in this Caſe, would diſcover, that you do not hate the Sin, ſo much, as ſeek an Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage againſt the Party you do not like. And it may give an Occaſion to others to raiſe the old Scandal, That you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve God ſees no Sin in his People, and therefore Men ſhould not: And that the Saints cannot Sin, nor Believers do them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves any harm by Sin: And being aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of eſcaping Eternal Puniſhment, they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98209:23"/> ought to be ſaved from Temporal. This would be the greateſt Reproach, on the Profeſſion of Religion that can be.</p>
            <p>AND withal take heed, not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute any Man that is Faulty in this Matter, becauſe he is your particular E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, or hath diſobliged, or injured you. For whatever he ſuffers in this Caſe, tho' he never ſo much deſerves it, what you do can never be pleaſing to GOD, as being from a wrong Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nor is it likely to reclaim the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender.</p>
            <p>NEITHER muſt you neglect Juſtice, becauſe the Offender is your Friend, or Acquaintance. Not that I would be thought to encourage you to betray Converſation, to be falſe to your Friend, and if an Offence be Committed only in your Preſence, to go preſently to a Magiſtrate, as an Accuſer. I ſhould think a faithful, friendly, and ſharp Reproof in that caſe, for the firſt or ſecond time at leaſt, may be ſufficient; if there be hopes of their Repentance. You will find Caſes enough, where is no ſuch Confidence ariſing from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and no danger of ſuch a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98209:24"/> Charge of Treachery to be objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your Proceedings.</p>
            <p n="3">3. LET me beſeech you to beware how you <hi>Tempt</hi> others to Sin, on a Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opſition that their Character is bad, and their Inclinations naught, and then Accuſe them for Complying with the Temptation which you offered, it may be with Artifice and Cunning, and the promiſe of Secrecy. 'Tis poſſible there may be Perſons of very ill Inclinations, who would have ſtopped there, if they had not been actually tempted. And there is an unſpeakable Hazard, leſt the Perſons that tempt in order to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, ſhould enter into the Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and fall into the ſnare of the Devil, and be overcome Themſelves. Take heed therefore of catching the Infection you would cure: Leſt, by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to ſnatch others out of the Fire, they pull you into it. God grant it never may be ſo.</p>
            <p n="4">4. THERE is another thing as to <hi>Impartiality,</hi> wherein your work may be difficult; and that is, that many are guilty of the ſame Crimes, who are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove your reach: Perſons of that Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98209:24"/> and Figure, Character and Intereſt in the World, that you dare not med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with them. For Drunkenneſs and Whoredom, Profane Swearing and Curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not the Vices only of Servants, but Maſters; not of meaner People only, but of your Equals and Superiors; not of thoſe that wear Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries, but of the Gentlemen whom they follow. <hi>I Anſwer,</hi> A little Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Reſolution, with Wiſdom and Prudence, may aſſiſt you to do your Duty as to this. Doubtleſs you will not think that you ought to keep the Favour and good Opinion of any ſuch, by conniving at their Faults, when it is in your power to puniſh, For what is an Offence againſt the Law of God and the Land in one Man, is ſo in another. But in ſome Caſes, as matters now are, where it would be likely to do more hurt than good, I think you may forbear: And believe, and hope that the Puniſhment of mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Perſons, will ſo far influence the Greater Sort, as to bring them to be more private, and leſs ſcandalous in their Crimes. And ſometimes the beſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98209:25"/> Rebuke that can be given ſome great Men and Superiours, is to let them ſee what is the juſt and deſerved Puniſhment of their own Faults, by the Puniſhment of Inferiours, for the ſame things which they know themſelves to be guilty of.</p>
            <p>AND thus I have, faithfully and plainly told you your Duty, with the principal Objections againſt it, and with the proper Limitations and Cautions. What remains, is to Exhort and Urge you to the Practice.</p>
            <p>SHALL I ſet before you the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Intereſt of the Kingdom? Or the Kindneſs to the particular Perſons who offend? Or the Honour of our Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and City? Or the juſt Expectations of GOD and all the World, after this Publick Peace? Or the Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Union of ſo many Worthy Members of the National Church with Proteſtant Diſſenters in this Undertak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? There are many things may be urged under all theſe Heads, ſuitable to our preſent purpoſe: I will name a few, and ſo Conclude.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:98209:25"/>
            <p n="1">I. THE publick Intereſt of the Community is maintained by the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of good Laws. The Welfare of Society, and its Publick Peace, cannot elſe be preſerved. The very Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by which you enjoy your many Bleſſings in a private Capacity, muſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe ſink. Gouts, and Palſies, and Conſumptions, and other Diſeaſes of the Body, are not more certainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the Health and Life of a particular Perſon, than the Impunity of Profane and Wicked People to the Peace and Happineſs of a State and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>THE Divine Preſence and Favour, (which is the Strength and Stability of a People,) cannot otherwiſe be ſecured, or his threatned Judgments diverted. Wicked Cities and Societies God will puniſh in <hi>this World,</hi> and, <hi>as ſuch,</hi> they cannot otherwiſe be puniſhed at all; tho' particular Perſons ſhall be accountable in <hi>another.</hi> The Crimes you endeavour to puniſh, you know, are ſuch, for which the Wrath of God
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98209:26"/> cometh upon the Children of Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: For which a flying Roll of Written-Curſes is declared to be ſent: For which other Lands have been made to mourn. And on the contrary, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuting Judgment for ſuch Offences, we read of Divine Judgments removed, and his Plagues ſtayed. A few, that would publickly and reſolutely own God and Religion, might have ſaved a City. <hi>If you can find a Man that executeth Judgment, and ſeeketh Truth, I will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don Jeruſalem,</hi> ſaith God by one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.5. <hi>I ſought for a Man, and found none to ſtand in the Gap, therefore I poured out mine Indignation upon them,</hi> ſaith another, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22. Though at the ſame time there was a Remnant, it may be, of Seven Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand unknown Perſons, that did ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly fear and worſhip God in their Hearts: But they did not preſerve the Nation from Captivity, and the City from Deſtruction, as a Few, openly and reſolutely owning God and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, would have done.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:98209:26"/>
            <p>BUT if GOD had not threaten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Judgment, ſuch a People would ſoon undo themſelves by their own Vices: Which muſt neceſſarily weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, divide, diſhonour, impoveriſh, and deſtroy them. Great Numbers of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, that in a time of War, might defend their Country, are effeminated, debauched, diſeaſed, and made unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of bearing Arms; fitter for an Hoſpital, than an Army; to be under a Phyſician, or Chyrurgeon, rather than a General; who inſtead of being able to uſe a Sword or Musket, need a Crutch. By unreſtrained, unpuniſhed Vice and Wickedneſs, the very Genius of a Nation is changed, a generous and brave People diſpirited: By Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Debauchery they are ſoftened and diſſolved into Cowardize: They loſe their Reputation abroad, and have no Strength at home; and are an eaſie Prey to Foreign Enemies: But, without that, muſt ſink under their own Burden, and in a little time will undo themſelves.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:98209:27"/>
            <p n="2">II. IT will be Kindneſs to the Particular Perſons, whoſe Manners are ſo corrupt as to come under the Laſh of the Law: For it is not of Capital Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments we now ſpeak. <hi>He that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth againſt God, wrongeth his own Soul.</hi> And is it no Kindneſs to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them from wounding, and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and deſtroying themſelves; from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming the Beauty, darkning the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, debaſing the Purity, weakning the Strength, diſturbing the Peace, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining the Life and Happineſs of their own Souls. 'Tis to hinder them from laying violent Hands on themſelves, who like mad Men would thruſt a Sword into their own Hearts. And yet how many ſuch Spectacles of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion are there, where Vice is not reſtrained and puniſhed? The Sight of a Wreck at Sea by a Tempeſt, or the Deſolations of a Country by War, (where their Cities have been plunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and Houſes burnt, and dead Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſes lay expoſed in the Field and Streets;) This would affect you with
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:98209:27"/> Compaſſion: But the unreſtrained Wickedneſs of the World, is a worſe Sight. To ſee a Man weltering in his own Blood, and gaſping for Breath, after he hath wounded and ſtabbed himſelf, is a doleful Sight; But the Sinfulneſs, and Miſery of Mankind by Reaſon of Sin, ſhould much rather move our Compaſſion.</p>
            <p>ARE you not kind to them? to ſave them from Beggery, from Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny, from Sickneſs, from Death, and from the Wrath of God for ever? Is it not kindneſs, to ſave them from languiſhing, painful Sickneſs? from Feavers and Dropſies, from Gouts and Cholicks, Conſumptions, and worſe Diſtempers, that are the Conſequents of their particular Vices, and of a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly Life? and withal to ſave them from an untimely Death by the Sword of Juſtice?</p>
            <p>'TIS impoſſible to tell from what Miſchiefs you preſerve a Man, who is reclaimed but from that <hi>one Vice</hi> of <hi>Drunkenneſs:</hi> For who knows what Miſchiefs and Deſtruction he may
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98209:28"/> run into, by running into that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; when once the Wine has filled him with more Spirits than he is able to govern? To be ſure, you ſave them from a great deal of Anguiſh and Trouble of Conſcience: For e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven they that laugh, and ſport, and drink away their Fears and Remorſe; yet when the Company is broken up, and the Heat of the Wine is over, their gloomy miſgiving Thoughts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn upon them, and they care not to be alone, or in the dark, for fear of their own guilty Selves.</p>
            <p>HOW many of theſe need to be pitied, eſpecially who have had <hi>a good Education;</hi> to whom it was more difficult to run into an exceſs of Riot: For they muſt ſtifle many more Convictions, and be at a great deal of Pains, to ſilence the Clamours of Conſcience; They muſt lay aſide Conſideration and ſerious Thoughts, forſake the Publick Aſſemblies for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, neglect the Reading of the Bible, avoid the ſerious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of thoſe that would reprove
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98209:28"/> them; They muſt leave off ſecret Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, they muſt accuſtom themſelves to looſe Converſation, and admit Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Atheiſm and Infidelity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they can adventure to commit ſome great Crimes. And it may be for a good while Conſcience will ſpeak louder in their Ears, and the Flames of Hell flaſh oftener, and more ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly in their Eyes, becauſe of <hi>their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation.</hi> They have much ado to hold on; and if they be ſick, or like to die, how ready are they to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair: Unleſs they leave the World like ſtupified Brutes, they are uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in moſt dreadful Agonies. Is it not kind, to pity 'em, and endeavour to ſave them from all this, and from E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Damnation after all?</p>
            <p>ARE you not kind to them, when you conſider they cannot be undone for ever by a ſinful Courſe, without being miſerable now, and you would fain preſerve them from both? Every Week's Experience will confirm the Truth of this. If Men reflect, and conſider what they have got by a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:98209:29"/> diſorderly Life: <hi>What Fruit</hi> have they had in the Way of Sin? Let them bring in their Account, and let us view the <hi>Sum Total.</hi> What Fruit have they had? but ſo much Shame and Fear, ſo much Care and Trouble, ſo much Diſgrace and Diſapointment, Diſſatisfaction and Diſquiet; ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sorrows and Calamities; an ill Name, an empty Purſe, a decayed For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, a diſeaſed Body, an accuſing Conſcience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And all theſe by ſuch Sins as you would reſtrain, puniſh, and prevent. And is it not Kindneſs, thus to convince them, that if they will periſh for ever, they muſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe Eternal Miſery by preſent Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; and run the Hazard at leaſt of being Undone in <hi>this World,</hi> that they may be Damned in <hi>the next?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. IS not the Honour of the City, and of the Nation, concerned in this? To revive thoſe Vertues which were anciently the Glory of <hi>England,</hi> and to check and reform thoſe Diſorders
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98209:29"/> which the Licentiouſneſs of the latter Reigns has introduced? Is Reverence for the Bleſſed God, his Name, his Word, his Day, his Inſtitutions; Is Honeſty, Truth and Juſtice, Sobriety, Temperance, and Chaſtity, leſs a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in our Age, than heretofore? Were theſe things only fit to be admired in former Times, without being practiſed in ours? 'Tis certainly for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>London,</hi> (which is one of the moſt conſiderable Cities in the World on other Accounts,) that baſe Aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, Murders, and Robberies, are not ſo common every Day and Night, here, as in many Cities of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy:</hi> That a Man may walk ſafely, upon a lawful Occaſion, at any time of the Night, from one end of the City to the other, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hazard of his Life by Piſtol or Stilletto. Would it not be a greater Honour to this City, (and the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion profeſſed here,) to be able to walk up and down, and not meet a Drunkard reeling in the Streets, or hear the GOD of Heaven blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:98209:30"/> or a prophane Oath ſworn in the Places of publick Concourſe? not to hear Men curſe and ſwear, and pray to GOD to damn them? (which is, and ſhould be the Buſineſs of their their Lives to eſcape and prevent.) On which account alſo common Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and publick Converſe is unea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to a Serious Chriſtian: For the Company of many witty and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Perſons muſt be declin'd, and avoided by a Man of Conſcience, by Reaſon of their Oaths and Curſes, and impious Language, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe would be both pleaſing and profitable. However, If we cannot go ſo far in ſuch a Reformation, as to hope to live to ſee all this; let us do <hi>what we can,</hi> and beg that the next Generation may carry it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. SHALL I urge you to theſe joint Endeavours for ſuppreſſing Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fneneſs, from the <hi>Seaſonableneſs</hi> of them, after the <hi>Publick Peace</hi> which GOD hath mercifully given us?
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98209:30"/> Many Penal Laws, in a time of War, are more faintly executed, becauſe the Government may ſtand in need of the Aſſiſtance of the Bad, as well as the Good: But when the Sword of War abroad is ſheathed, that of Civil Juſtice ſhould be drawn againſt <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faneneſs,</hi> becauſe the Government has occaſion only for the Service of <hi>Good Men</hi> in a time of <hi>Peace:</hi> And hath not ſo much other Buſineſs to divert them from executing the Laws. So that not to puniſh Vice in a time of Peace, will be a greater Reflection on the Government, than if the War had continued. And alas, how little Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity can we have of the Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Peace, or of any of the Bleſſings of it, without Reformation? <hi>Is it Peace, Jehu?</hi> Is there, can there be a laſting well-grounded <hi>Peace,</hi> while Whoredoms and Adulteries, Perjuries and Blaſphemies, profane Oaths and Curſes, and other Abominations, <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed,</hi> are ſo many?</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:98209:31"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Conſider, Theſe are Things that <hi>we All Agree in.</hi> The viſible Countenance of ſo many worthy Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, of different Perſwaſions in leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Things, thus to abet the Cauſe of Religion, and to diſcourage Profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is a Great Thing. It may help to bring Sobriety and Serious Godlineſs into requeſt. Whereas if good Men be timorous and baſhful, if they be afraid, or aſhamed to take the Part of Religion, (tho' the Laws of GOD are ſeconded by thoſe of the Nation;) the Profligate and Profane will be more hardened, more numerous and inſolent. For there is hardly any thing does more embolden Men in Sin, than to ſee Others commit the like with Impunity. And we may juſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, that the ſpreading of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery in City and Country, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much owing to this: That Good Men, who are inwardly Friends to Religion, ſtand <hi>Neuters,</hi> and will not concern themſelves to appear againſt Profaneneſs, and help to ſtem the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98209:31"/> Tide. 'Tis in this Caſe, as one ſays of <hi>a Plague,</hi> If the Sound and Heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy will withdraw themſelves in a time of Infection, and do nothing to ſtop the Peſtilence; if only the Sick and Infected do walk abroad, and appear in publick; how unavoida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly muſt the Contagion ſpread, and the Plague reign, even to Deſolation, in ſuch a place?</p>
            <p>I AM not without hope, that this laudable and Chriſtian Undertaking will promote a better Underſtanding between the Proteſtants of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Church, and Thoſe who in ſome things diſſent from it. As far as we have attained, let us agree to mind the ſame thing. And to ſuppreſs Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality and Profaneneſs, I am ſure, is one of thoſe things, wherein we <hi>ought,</hi> and <hi>may,</hi> and <hi>do</hi> Agree. And by more familiar Acquaintance with one another, you may find ſo many Perſons, of both ſorts, worthy of your Eſteem and Love, as will take off many Prejudices, deſtroy Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Rancor, and cure that Evil
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98209:32"/> ſpeaking and Detraction, which hath been complained of on all ſides; It may tend to heal that Moroſeneſs, and Reſervedneſs, and Diſtruſt of one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, which has kept us at ſuch a Diſtance: And let us ſee, that there was no ſufficient reaſon for ſuch an Eſtrangment. I promiſe my ſelf, that Diſſenters will be ſo wiſe and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, as to be of <hi>Luther</hi>'s mind; When ſo much was done at <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purg,</hi> towards an Agreement between him and the <hi>Helvetians,</hi> he ſaid on that Occaſion, that he would not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that Praiſe to the other Party, to be more deſirous of Peace and Concord than he. There is the more ground to hope for this, in the preſent Age, becauſe we agree in the <hi>Myſtery of GOD, even of the Father, and the Lord JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S CHRIST,</hi> I mean in the Doctrinal Articles of <hi>The Church of England;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon we have ſufficient ground, that <hi>our Hearts be knit together in Love,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Coll.</hi> 2.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:98209:32"/>
            <p>'TIS high time, <hi>My Brethren,</hi> to lay aſide our paltry Quarrels, and Contentions with one another, and ſeek the Common Good; and mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to make Allowance for the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Complexions of Mens Minds, and their different degrees of Light, for the Variety of their Tempers and Educations, for different Growths, and Meaſures, and Attainments in Chriſtianity, in order to mutual For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance of one another in Love. For it can never be denied, that, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Thoſe of different Perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons among Chriſtians, there may be, and is, the ſame deſire and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in ſearching after Truth, the ſame Love to GOD and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votedneſs to him, and deſire to pleaſe him, the ſame Integrity and Purity of Intention, the ſame Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart and Life, which is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of God. And ſhall any of us be ſo diſingenuous and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, as to think none can get to Heaven, but Chriſtians juſt of our ſize, form, and way? Or ſhall I be ſo
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:98209:33"/> peeviſh and abſurd, as to be angry with another Man, becauſe he is not of my Opinion, when he hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very whit as much Reaſon, (that is, none at all,) to be angry with me for not being of his? The want of conſidering theſe things, and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on holding the Unity of the Spirit in the bond of Peace, hath more wounded Religion, and hindred the Progreſs of it, and been more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to its National Intereſt, than all the Oppoſition of Infidels and Hereticks, that have openly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacked the Reformed Doctrine. If all Good Men, amongſt Proteſtants, would reſolve to love one another, and bear with one another in their leſſer Differences; you would quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee that Truth would more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, and Holineſs with it. For un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Love to all Men, and a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Love to good Men, according to their ſeveral degrees of Worth and Goodneſs; is ſo agreeable to Reaſon, to the Social Nature, and common Intereſt of Mankind, and to the Rule
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:98209:33"/> and Pattern of our Bleſſed Saviour; that it muſt needs not only be gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally approv'd, but have a mighty Influence to make the World better, and to recover the Beauty and Glory, of the Chriſtian Reformed Religion in theſe Nations.</p>
            <p>IT may therefore humble and ſhame us, to think we have been ſo little able to bear with one another in our leſſer Differences; when we take a View of the miſerable Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the World, and of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches, in other Parts of the Earth. Hath not Paganiſm and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometaniſm over-run a great part, which was once a Chriſtian, but hath now loſt the very Name? And is not a great part of Chriſtendom o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-run with Popiſh Tyranny and Superſtition, and thereby hath little left of Chriſtianity, but the Name? Is there any part of God's Earth, where Chriſtian Religion doth flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, more than in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland?</hi> And ſhall we not at laſt be ſo wiſe and happy, as to know
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:98209:34"/> the Things that belong to our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſt? Are we not Members of the ſame Myſtical Body, and Servants of the ſame Lord, Profeſſors of the ſame Faith, Partakers of the ſame Hope, and Heirs of the ſame Promiſe of Eternal Life, by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> And beſides this, united by a National In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, at this Day, to hold together againſt the common Enemies of our Chriſtian Faith on the one hand, and the common Enemies of our Country, and Civil Liberties on the other?</p>
            <p>To Conclude, Let me beſeech and intreat you, from all that has been ſaid, to go on with Courage, under the Banner of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and with the Prayers of all good Men: Continue in the Love of GOD, and Zeal for his Glory, in Love and Loyalty to the King's Majeſty, and in Peace and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord one with another. Let us join with united Hearts for the Publick Good; and, forgetting all that is paſt, reſolve to look forward. Fear not to diſpleaſe Men, if you may but ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God. Be as diligent to check
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:98209:34"/> and reſtrain Vice, as others are to ſpread it; as knowing how much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Maſter you ſerve, and how much better Work it is, to endeavour to ſave the Church and State, the Souls and Bodies of Men, than to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in hurting and deſtroying them. And be ſure begin at home, at your own Souls, and Lives, and then as to your Families, and Relations of ſeveral ſorts in this City. And on that account, where you have a Vote, omit not your Duty in the Choice of good Magiſtrates; as knowing <hi>where the Righteous bear Rule, the People re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce.</hi> They who are negligent in this, and other Inſtances of Publick Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, which their Place and Station in this City call them to, they betray their Country, are unfaithful to their Truſt, and ſhall anſwer to God for their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſive Treachery.</p>
            <p>YOU have begun well, remember the Reward of being faithful. Let not your Hearts fail; for <hi>he that follows af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Righteouſneſs and Mercy, he ſhall find Life, Righteouſneſs and Honour.</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:98209:35"/> And tho' you ſhould fail of the deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Succeſs of your Endeavours, (which you have no Reaſon to think, by the excellent Service that has been done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready,) ſo as to loſe your Labour and your Coſt; you will not loſe your Charity and your Zeal: For GOD will Accept you. To his gracious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, Promiſe, and Spirit, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you, for your Aſſiſtance, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, and Reward.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit, be Everlaſting Glory.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 23. l. 4. for <hi>Societies</hi> r. <hi>Society.</hi> Pag. 56. l. 6. dele <hi>their.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:98209:35"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> at the <hi>Angel,</hi> in the <hi>Poultrey.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>MR. <hi>Shower</hi>'s Winter Meditations: Or, a Sermon, concerning <hi>Froſt,</hi> and <hi>Snow,</hi> and <hi>Winds, &amp;c.</hi> and the Wonders of God therein. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               <item>— His Thankſgiving Sermon, <hi>April</hi> 16. 1696. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— His Account of the LIFE of Mr. <hi>Henry Gearing.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— His Diſcourſe of Tempting CHRIST. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— His Diſcourſe of Family Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In Three Letters. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— His Sermon on the Death of Mr. <hi>Nathanael Oldfeild,</hi> who departed <hi>Dec.</hi> 21. 1696.</item>
               <item>— His Sermon to the <hi>Societies</hi> for the Reformation of Manners. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Pool</hi>'s Engliſh Annotations, with the Addition of Contents, and a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordance by Mr. <hi>Clark.</hi> In 2 Vol. <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Life of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Baxter,</hi> written by himſelf. <hi>Fol.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:98209:36"/>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Lorimer</hi>'s Apology for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, who ſubſcribed only unto the Stating of the Truth and Errors in Mr. <hi>William</hi>'s Book, in Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Trail</hi>'s Letter to a Miniſter in the Country. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Lorimer</hi>'s Remarks on Mr. <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win</hi>'s Anſwer to the Apology, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that the Goſpel-Covenant is a Law of Grace. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Slater</hi>'s Thankſgiving Sermon, <hi>Octob.</hi> 27. 1692. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>— His Sermons at the Funerals of Mr. <hi>John Reynolds,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Fincher,</hi> Miniſters of the Goſpel. 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Burton</hi>'s Diſcourſes of Purity, Charity, Repentance, and ſeeking firſt the Kingdom of God. Publiſhed with a Preface by Dr. <hi>John Tillotſon,</hi> late Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Wilkin</hi>'s Diſcourſe of the Gift of Prayer and Preaching, the latter much inlarged by the Biſhop of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich</hi> and <hi>Chicheſter.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Samuel Slater</hi>'s Earneſt Call to Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily Religion; being the Subſtance of Eighteen Sermons. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:98209:36"/>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Addy</hi>'s <hi>Stenograpia:</hi> Or, the Art of Short-writing, compleated in a far more Compendious way than any yet extant, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In which Character is alſo Printed the whole Bible, by Mr. <hi>Addy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cambridge</hi> Phraſes; being a full and large Phraſe-Book for the uſe of Schools. By <hi>Will. Robertſon.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Gibbon</hi>'s Sermon of <hi>Juſtification.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Nat. Vincent</hi>'s Funeral Sermon, Preached by Mr. <hi>Nat. Taylor.</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Woodhouſe</hi>'s Sermon, to the <hi>Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> for Reformation of Manners. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A faithful Rebuke to a falſe Report, lately written and diſperſed (by <hi>Stephen Lob</hi>) in a Letter to a Friend in the Country. Concerning ſeveral Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences in Doctrinals, between ſome Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Miniſters in <hi>London.</hi> By a Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Divine. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Geo. Hammond</hi>'s and Mr. <hi>Math. Barker</hi>'s Diſcourſes of Family Worſhip. Written at the Requeſt of the United Miniſters of <hi>London.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Remarks on a late Diſcourſe of <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam,</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>London-Derry,</hi> concerning the Inventions of Men in the Worſhip of God. Alſo a Defence
<pb facs="tcp:98209:37"/> of the ſaid Remarks againſt his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's Admonition. By <hi>T. Boyſe.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>London Diſpenſatory</hi> reduced to the Practice of the <hi>London</hi> Phyſicians. By <hi>John Peachey,</hi> of the College of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, <hi>London.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Dying Man's Aſſiſtant: Or, ſhort Inſtructions for thoſe who are concerned in preparing ſick Perſons for Death. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Samuel Clark</hi>'s brief Concordance to the whole Bible, in a new Method. 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Robert Howard</hi>'s Free Diſcourſe; wherein the Doctrines that make for Tyranny are diſplay'd, and the Title of our Lawful and Rightful King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> Vindicated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hyſtroſtaticks:</hi> Or, Inſtructions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Water-works. Collected out of the Papers of Sir <hi>Sam. Morland.</hi> 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:98209:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
